Good ערב ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Erev Rosh
Hashanah*, today's דף daf *Daf* is צ״ד *Tzadi-Dalet*. We begin a little
bit behind on צ״ג עמוד ב׳ *Tzadi-Gimmel Amud Bet*, אין הטבחים נאמנים
*Ein HaTabachim Ne'emanin*, and the משנה Mishna's *Mishna* was saying that the
butchers cannot be trusted to remove the גיד הנשה gid hanashe, *Gid
HaNasheh* and the חכמים *Chachamim* say because it's a pain and the
חכמים *Chachamim* say that they can. Let's take a look. אמר רבי
Rabbi חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Chiya Bar Abba
Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, חזרו לומר נאמנים *Chazru Lomar
Ne'emanim* that they are believed. אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav Nachman*, אכשורי
דרי *Achshurei Darei*? What, you think that people have gotten frummer?
So that's pretty חס ושלום *Chas V'Shalom*, חס ושלום *Chas V'Shalom*, but
what are you thinking? People, you know, is that really the trajectory
that people get frummer? So that's a good מוסר *Mussar* right for
ערב ראש השנה *Erev Rosh Hashanah*. Anyway, so it says מעיקרא סברוה
כרבי מאיר *Me'ikara Savruha K'Rabbi Meir*. Now here's what happened. Originally they
held like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. Now you'll remember רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* said that you have to dig after the גיד הנשה gid
hanashe, *Gid HaNasheh* and get all the tiny little branches. So originally
they held like him ולא הוו מהימני *V'la Havai Mehemnei*, then they
couldn't be trusted because that was too, it was too demanding. ובסוף
סברי כרבי יהודה *U'vesof Savri K'Rabbi Yehuda*, then the פסק *Pesak* shifted
and the position became like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. And now the
position is רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, it's just taking out the big
גיד gid. *Gid*, not all the tiny little branches. It's very easy,
so then they could be trusted. Okay. איכא דמתני לה לסיפא *Ika
DeMatni Lah L'Seifa*, some say that this goes, that this sort of
discussion, similar type of discussion took place at the end of the
משנה Mishna's *Mishna*. The חכמים *Chachamim*'s position: וחכמים אומרים נאמנים עליו ועל
החלב *V'Chachamim Omrim Ne'emanin Alav V'Al HaChelev*. They can be trusted. So
that's starting with the position that you can't trust them. אמר רבי
חייא *Amar Rabbi Chiya* said רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Chiya Bar Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, חזרו לומר אין נאמנים *Chazru
Lomar Ein Ne'emanim*. Then they reversed themselves and said they couldn't be
trusted. Ah, okay, that fits with our assumption that people sort of
get less frum. אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav Nachman*, but then came
רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* and said בזמן הזה *Bizman Hazeh* נאמנים *Ne'emanim*,
they can be trusted, going back to what it was in the
משנה mishna, *Mishna*. So becoming less frum and then getting back to
the old standard. So again the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אכשורי דרי
*Achshurei Darei*? What? Okay, frummer? So even just getting back to an
old standard the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is skeptical about. So it says
מעיקרא סברוה כרבי יהודה *Me'ikara Savruha K'Rabbi Yehuda*, originally they held like
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, so therefore the butchers could be trusted, it
was easy to get rid of the גיד gid. *Gid*. והשתא סברוה
כרבי מאיר *V'hashta Savruha K'Rabbi Meir*, then they went back to hold
like, then they went, not back, then they went to hold like
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that said you had to dig after it
and that meant that the butchers were not being able to be
trusted that they would do that. קמיה דהוה דכירי ליה לרבי יהודה
*Kamei Dehava Dechirei Leih L'Rabbi Yehuda*, but however here was the problem,
this is very interesting
socially and psychologically. A couple of people even when the פסק *Pesak*
shifted to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, a couple of the butchers used
to remember לרבי יהודה *L'Rabbi Yehuda*. Those that remembered that said, "What
are you talking about all this new חומרות *Chumras*, new nonsense רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*? We know what you have to do to remove
the גיד gid *Gid*," and they would just remove the main גיד
gid. *Gid* and they wouldn't remove the branches because they lived in
a time when everybody was ruling like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. So
they basically, you know, rejected either consciously or subconsciously were not able
to, you know, were not able to adapt to the new standard.
So then therefore you couldn't trust butchers because some were still doing
the old standard. והשתא דאנשיוה לרבי יהודה
*V'hashta D'anshivah L'Rabbi Yehuda*, now that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* has been forgotten, once, you know, some more
time passed and and all the old guard passed away and now
you only have the new generation and all they know of is
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So now מהימני *Mehemnei*, now you can trust
them.
The lenient מסורה *Mesorah* was lost. What? The lenient מסורה *Mesorah*.
The lenient מסורה *Mesorah* was lost. So what's interesting though about this
shift, besides that that's pretty, you know, I think a, you know,
an insightful description about the psychology and so
on, but but I think what's also interesting is that the upshot
of this is that the ruling is like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*,
whereas the upshot of the previous theory was that the ruling was
like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. So there's a big נפקא מינה *Nafka
Mina* in terms of that. Yeah.
And when רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* as a named תנא *Tana* disputes
a, disputes another תנא *Tana*, the הלכה halacha *Halacha* is almost never
like him. Right. Exactly. And the second thing is quoting רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*, isn't he, isn't he in many places in ש״ס *Shas*
talking about ירידת הדורות *Yeridat HaDorot* and how things are not like
they used to be?
Yeah, who's the primary speaker of the whole concept of ירידת הדורות
*Yeridat HaDorot* is the question? Also, question about whether ירידת הדורות *Yeridat
HaDorot*, you know, how much that means about intellect, how much it
means about observance, but you are right that the very fact, you
know, there's a whole question about
how how much the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is hard subscribed to the
principle of ירידת הדורות *Yeridat HaDorot*. Clearly the fact that here it
sort of finds it shocking that
that there could be a period where people became frummer from an
earlier period, from an earlier, you know, in the תנאי *Tannai*... I
you know, is exactly reflecting of a, you know, very sort of
deep assumption that people, you know, in general this sense of ירידה
*Yerida*. You're absolutely right about that. And I know Michael's going to
ask how we פסקן *Pasken*, of course I did not get a
chance to check that up,
so I will happily get back to you on that.
But we're אשכנזים *Ashkenazim*, don't we לבבר *L'vaber*?
Well right, but the question is do we not bother because... Because
we rule like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. You know, if it were
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* it wouldn't be so hard. So is that
why we don't bother?
And also like, right, and what's about טבחים *tabbachim* then, you know,
they cannot be trusted.
Right, well, it is, well, basically, but then nowadays we don't trust
טבחים *tabbachim* even for things that aren't difficult. Like we need, you
know, משגיחים *mashgiachim*. So that, you know, when we learn the משנה
mishna *Mishnah*, we pointed out that the general assumption that where it's
not difficult, we would trust and don't need a הכשר *hechsher*, even
though it's something that a person has a financial interest in, you
know, is is surprising. But again, the very fact that the משנה
mishna *Mishnah* also reflects the fact that מציאות *metzius*, the context, you
know, means that you might have to re-evaluate some of those standard
standard הלכה *halachic* presumptions. So even though עד אחד נאמן באיסורין *ed
echad ne'eman b'issurin*, in certain contexts not. So you know, the whole
הכשר *hechsher* industry, well not the whole because when it but when
it applies to, let's say, Jewish-owned, you know,
observant Jewish-owned kosher restaurants, and the fact that you still need a
השגחה *hashgacha*, basically, says we don't go by עד אחד נאמן באיסורין
*ed echad ne'eman b'issurin*. We go by that if it's financial, you
know, interest and there's a יצר הרע *yetzer hara* and there's things
that are difficult or whatever. So that sort of encapsulates. Because if
they have a financial interest...
Well, that raises certain questions about the payment of the משגיח *mashgiach*
and how that works and whether the משגיח *mashgiach* can take certain
can take meals from the restaurant. And so they try to address
those issues. That's our question. Okay. But yeah, it seems basically though,
I mean, not just because of the פשט pshat *pshat* of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the way it was quoted earlier, you know,
that and I see that we rule like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*.
I assume we do. I have to be honest, I didn't get
a chance to check, but the very fact that we never even
bother with the removing of the גיד gid *gid* and all of
the sort of, you know, the theme of all of these, I
think the the more dominant position in these גמרות Gemaras *Gemoros* is
the מחטט אחריו *mechateit acharav*. So it certainly is my presumption that
we rule that, but I'm not I haven't I haven't had a
chance to review that, so there might be some ראשונים *Rishonim* that
disagree.
And what about the in one the out one, you know, that...
What? You remember there was like the two גידים *gidim*, you know.
Yeah, the outer one is still not the גיד gid *gid*. We
never said the outer one was the גיד gid *gid*.
We still don't know...
What? ואל החלב פשיטא peshita? דשכיח חלב מהימן דכוותיה שמעיה *v'al hacheilev
pishata d'shachiah cheilev m'heiman dachvosei shemaya*. What do you mean by whether
they can be trusted about the fat, who mentioned the fat? הכי
קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, and this is what it means: אינו נאמן לא
על החלב *eino ne'eman lo al hacheilev*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says
they can't be trusted on the fat, on the גיד gid. *gid*
or the fat. וחכמים אומרים נאמנים הם על החלב *v'Chachamim omrim ne'emanim
hem al hacheilev*. They can be trusted on the fat. So the
question is which fat? So if it's the fat of the גיד
gid *gid*, you understand that those are linked debates because however you
have to dig after the גיד gid *gid*, you have to dig
after the fat of the גיד *gid*. However, תוספות *Tosafot* says that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, if you remember we had this before, denies
that there's an even a מנהג *minhag* about the fat, that the
fat is totally permissible. So it wouldn't be a question about being
believed. תוספות *Tosafot* says this means the general question about believing them
about removing the חלב *cheilev*, but then it's not so clear how
these positions are linked. How the position about whether they can be
trusted about the גיד *gid*, which has to deal with digging after
the גיד *gid*, is linked to the question about removing the fat
where everybody agrees, you know, that the fat is a that the
fat is a problem. So תוספות *Tosafot*, you know, sort of deals
with this. He doesn't really have a full explanation about how they're
linked, but he does point out of course, you know, that רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* in general just has is a little either skeptical
about... right, either his standards about what you need to do are
higher or he's skeptical about whether people are going to meet those
standards. So it's not exactly connected to the earlier issue about how
far you have to dig after the גיד *gid*, because here it's
applied even to the issue of the fat. Okay, now we move
on to the next משנה mishna, *Mishnah*. And finally we're getting to
today's official דף *daf*. שולח אדם ירך לנכרי וגיד הנשה בתוכה מפני
שמקומו ניכר *sholeach adam yerech lenachri vegid hanasheh besocha mipnei shemekomo nikar*.
A person can send a thigh of an animal to a non-Jew
even without removing the גיד הנשה gid hanashe. *Gid HaNasheh* because you
can see it's obvious where the גיד *gid* is. Meaning it's not
something like you can't send, meaning as opposed to a טריפה treifa
*treifa*. You slaughtered an animal, can you send it to a non-Jew?
And the concern would be no, because the non-Jew will turn it
back around and send and sell it to a Jew. And there's
no no obvious sign that it is a טריפה treifa *treifa*. Now,
we're going to see in a minute, you know, maybe there were
ways in which the community can let it be known that that
טריפות treifos *treifos* were sold to non-Jews and people wouldn't buy. But
without that type of and that's the type of I'm expecting the
question to be, so how nowadays, you know, do we sell the
טריפות treifos, *treifos* to a non-Jew? Well, because nowadays nobody הוה אמינא
*hava amina* to buy anything that from a, you know, anything that
doesn't have a הכשר *hechsher* on it, so there's no question. But
when there was a you could actually let's say be in a
city that all of the butchers were kosher butchers and Jewish butchers,
you, you know, there might have been the possibility you could buy
things even coming from non-Jews because of the the assumption is they're
only getting it from the kosher butcher. So maybe they bought a
thigh of something and then they decided they didn't want it, and
you know, it's not like you just get it shipped in, where
else are they going to buy it except from the kosher butcher?
So then you could go back and buy it from them. So
the only thing you can't is you couldn't sell them a טריפה
treifa, *treifa* because then if the word didn't get out, they would
turn back and sell it to a Jew. But you could sell
them the thigh with the גיד הנשה gid hanashe *Gid HaNasheh*, because
if they try to sell it back to a Jew, the Jew
will see the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh. *Gid HaNasheh* and remove it
himself.
It's so much more obvious then. Right, and it's not a טריפה
treifa, *treifa*, correct.
Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now deals with the larger context in which people
will or will not assume that it's okay to buy from the
non-Jew.
So basically, you see a thigh, you know the גיד *gid* is
in there. So therefore...
Well, you can see the גיד *gid*.
Right,
or if the
גיד *gid*, right, exactly, so therefore you won't come to
buy it. implicitly or directly you know that the גיד is still
there. And then fine, buy it and remove the גיד. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: שלמה אין חתוכה לא. shleima in khatukha lo.
You can sell them a whole thigh but not a chopped up
one. במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what are we talking about? אילימא במקום
שאין מכריזין, ilema bemakom she-ein makhrizim, if it's a place where they
don't make announcements. What are these announcements? Announcements are: we sold a
טריפה treifa. today to non-Jews, and we'll see in a minute like
in the bottom of today's דף how they do it in a
little more subtle way. But basically the announcement is we sold some
טריפות treifas, to non-Jews today and be aware, meaning don't buy, you
know, don't buy meat from the non-Jew. I don't know whether that
is for a day, for a week, but wherever for whatever the
reasonable period is, be aware that they just got—we just sold them
some טריפות, treifas so don't purchase meat from them.
So a non-Jew or, you know, if he knew which ones...
the non-Jews in this community... No, they might have sold it to
one another, whatever. Once you know that there's a טריפה treifa, out
there, you have to be aware until we can assume that it's
been consumed, I guess. I don't know exactly what that period is
because people preserve their meat etc. So anyway, but there's an assumption
that that would put people on guard for the right amount of
time. So if that's the context, חתוכה נמי לישרי ליה. khatukha nami
lishari lei. So therefore why not even sell them a chopped up
side? Why? דלא אתו למזבן מיניה. de-lo asu limizban minei. So if
it's after—if it's a place שאין מכריזין, she-ein makhrizim, that starts if
it's the place where they don't make announcements. So if they don't
make announcements, you can never buy from non-Jews, right? Because if they
don't make announcements, any day the non-Jew might have טריפות, treifas. that's
today. If the non-Jew might have טריפות treifas in their hands, so
therefore you can never buy from them. Since you can never buy
from them anyway, sell them when it's got a גיד הנשה, Gid
Hanasheh, you can sell them a טריפה, treifa? sell them when it's
got a גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh Jews aren't going to buy from
it. חתוכה נמי לישרי ליה, khatukha nami lishari lei, sell them a
chopped up side. דלא אתו למזבן מיניה, de-lo asu limizban minei,
nobody's going to buy from them. אלא במקום שמכריזין, ela bemakom she-makhrizim,
it's a place where they do make announcements. So if they do
make announcements, when there's no announcement, you're allowed to buy from them.
And there the concern is you'll buy this animal because it's—it's not
a טריפה, treifa, there's been no announcement, but it's got a גיד
הנשה. Gid Hanasheh? Okay, so שלמה, shleima, so the גמרא Gemara. says:
Okay, I get it. But שלמה נמי לא לישרי ליה, shleima nami
lo lishari lei, why should he be allowed to sell them even
a whole thigh?
Why? דחתיך ליה ומזבין ליה. de-khatikh lei u-mazbin lei. I was expecting
you to ask this question Michael. So what, you sold them a
whole side? They'll just chop it up and sell it back to
the Jews, right? So they'll make it into into hamburger meat. So
it's a place where Jews will buy from non-Jews because they'll make
announcements, and don't sell it to them chopped up because they won't
see the גיד. Sell with the גיד so that when a Jew
buys it, he'll know that it's got the גיד. Okay, so how
can you do that?
And you can't say oh people know not to buy chopped up
meat, because then it wouldn't have told me that it's אסור assur
for me to sell it to him chopped up. The fact that
I can't sell it to the non-Jew chopped up means that the
next Jew can buy it from him chopped up, right? Or else
I'd be allowed to... everybody get that? If the non-Jew—if people didn't
buy chopped up meat, then I'd be allowed to sell it to
the non-Jew. If I can't sell it, it means that a Jew
can buy chopped—if a Jew can buy chopped up meat from the
non-Jew, why can I sell it to him whole? He'll just chop
it up. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: אי בעית
אימא, i ba'it eima, what?
unless they... some kind of you can't buy it from...
No, but then I should be allowed to sell—if you can't buy
chopped up meat from the non-Jew, I can sell it to the
non-Jew. So the fact that I can't sell the chopped up meat
to the non-Jew, it's got to be because a Jew is allowed
to buy it. But if a Jew is allowed to buy it,
why can I sell the whole meat? He'll just chop it up.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אי בעית אימא, i ba'it eima, if
you want I'll say במקום שאין מכריזין, bemakom she-ein makhrizim, they don't
announce and normally it's אסור assur to buy from non-Jews. אי בעית
אימא במקום שמכריזין, i ba'it eima bemakom she-makhrizim, or it's a case
where they do announce and normally it's מותר. muttar. Okay, so let's
see, did I skip a line? אי בעית אימא במקום שמכריזין אי
בעית אימא במקום שאין מכריזין. i ba'it eima bemakom she-makhrizim i ba'it
eima bemakom she-ein makhrizim. No, I just skipped forward. Either it's a
place where they do announce or it's a place where they don't
announce, I'll explain it both ways. אי בעית אימא במקום שמכריזין, i
ba'it eima bemakom she-makhrizim, let's say it's a place where they do
announce, so normally you're allowed to buy from non-Jews and here's the
difference between selling whole and selling chopped. חיתוכא דעכו"ם מידע ידיע, khitukha
de-akum mi-da yedia,
people will know, it looks different the way the non-Jews chop up
their meat. Now we are not obviously assuming hamburger meat. If we're
assuming hamburger meat, I assume there's nothing particularly distinctive about that. But
we are assuming that it means, you know, you know you don't
buy a side of beef, you buy it like you get it
at the butcher store, you know, you get a rib steak and
you get this and you get certain shops. So presumably there was
a Jewish way that it was distinctive in the way sort of
the Jews actually did the chopping and the way the non-Jews. So
you could tell if it's been—if you buy it from the non-Jew,
you will be able to tell whether it was chopped by a
Jew or chopped by a non-Jew. So the point is why can
I sell a whole thing to a Jew but not a chopped
up? If I sell chopped up to the non-Jew, to a non-Jew,
then the next Jew will buy it from him and he says
look, the Jew chopped it up, so nothing to worry about. He
must have removed the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh or whatever. But
if I sell it whole to a non-Jew and now... he sells
it to a Jew. So if he sells it whole the Jew
will see the גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. If he sells it chopped
up, then the Jew will say, oh, one minute, I can tell
that the non-Jew is the one that chopped this up. I don't
know, maybe there was a גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh maybe it wasn't
removed, I don't know the story, I'd better not buy it. Okay,
so therefore, it would be obvious that, I mean, and by the
way, although that might seem a little far-fetched that people are going
to be on their toes about that, but remember we also said
it's a מקום שמכריזין, makom shemakhrizin, which means it's a community already
that is sort of sensitive to these realities that knows normally you
can buy from a non-Jew, but when they make an announcement you
can't, because that means that they might have a טריפה. treifa. So
if they're sort of already attuned to being sensitive to these things,
they could also say, and if I see that the non... I
see that it was chopped up by the non-Jew, I have to
be afraid that maybe it had a גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh and
now it can't be seen anymore.
Except how is that non-Jew not getting like a whole, you know,
whatever it is, something?
They're only getting stuff local, correct. The assumption in all this is
they're only getting stuff locally from the kosher butchers. Okay, ואיבעית אימא
במקום שאין מכריזין, ve'iba'it eima bimkom she'ein makhrizin, that's one explanation. Another
explanation is a place where they don't make announcements, so normally people
can't buy. So if people can't buy, why should I not be
able to sell the meat to a... the thing with the גיד
הנשה? Gid Hanasheh So it says, גזירה שמא יתננה לפני ישראל אחר.
gezeira shema yitnena lifnei Yisrael akher.
So I'm afraid that although normally people can't buy from non-Jews, that's
because, you know, there's no announcements and they don't know if they
have טריפות. treifas But if you see me selling to my friend
the non-Jew and you happen to right there be in my butcher
store at that moment, so you'll just turn around and say, I
wanted that cut. Can you sell it back to me? or whatever,
something of that nature. So there, if it's got a גיד הנשה
Gid Hanasheh? in it and it's whole, you'll buy it right back
from him sort of, you know, you know the cut. You're only
buying... you're only being able to allowed to buy because you're buying
exactly the cut that you saw me sell. So if you buy
it back whole, then you'll see the גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh, If
I, however, I sold it chopped up and then you're going to
buy it back, you won't see the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh and
you're going to assume, since there was no announcement or whatever, you're
going to assume that it is okay. Okay, now the question of
course is that why then are we not wor... no...
well, the question then becomes really why are you allowed to... why
is it... why would people assume they could buy stuff? Oh, okay,
no, no, that's the answer. No, no, it's not. Okay, since the
מקום שאין מכריזין, makom she'ein makhrizin, since the מקום שאין מכריזין, makom
she'ein makhrizin, you're never going to know if there's טריפות or not.
Why would you be able to turn around and buy it from
the non-Jew, even if you saw me sell it? Why wouldn't you
have to be concerned that it's a טריפה, treifa. right? If that's
the context, that we don't announce when there are טריפות being sold
to a non-Jew, even if you saw me sell it to a
non-Jew, why
wouldn't you have to be concerned that it's a טריפה? treifa, So
again, unless the explanation here is that maybe you saw me sell
this chop, this side to the non-Jew, and I was selling from
the same animal to the Jews, you know, that could be the
context. So normally you saw me sell something to a non-Jew, you
couldn't turn around and buy from him. You'd have to be concerned
I sold him a טריפה, treifa, right? It's a מקום שאין מכריזין.
makom she'ein makhrizin. But if you saw me sell... from you, you
know, you see me, I mean, it's not like now everything is
nice and prepackaged. I'm going back into the room and I'm chopping
off this side and selling it to the non-Jew, and I'm chopping
off another part and selling it to a Jew, you see it's
not a טריפה. treifa So you see a lot of stuff then.
You could be seen...
I know, there has to be...
you've seen me just selling to the non-Jew,
it could be the whole thing is a טריפה. treifa Right, well,
exactly. So it has to be a specific context where we're afraid
you'll see me sell the side to a non-Jew and you'll have
seen me use the other part of the animal to Jews. And
in that type of a case, you might turn around and buy
it from him. So it's important that, so if I sold it
chopped up, you won't know to be on your toes. If I
sold it to him whole, you'll see the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh,
and it's got a problem. Okay,
let's keep on going. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, if you want I
can say, משום דקגניב ליה לדעתיה. mishum dekaganiv lei leda'atei.
Totally different explanation and this is going to lead to an unexpected
and fascinating digression of the גמרא, Gemara a very important one, maybe
to also think about our ראש השנה in terms of things we
might all want to work better on. So this is a concern
that you might be, forget it, Jews aren't going to buy. Okay,
it's a מקום שאין מכריזין, makom she'ein makhrizin, no Jew ever buys
from a non-Jew, no issue about a Jew buying. So why do
I care if whether I've removed the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh, or
not removed the גיד הנשה? gid hanasheh. Because you don't want to
mislead the non-Jew and do גניבת דעת. gneivat da'at. What does גניבת
דעת gneivat da'at mean? גניבת דעת gneivat da'at literally means stealing, burgling
the somebody's knowledge, meaning it's sort of like causing... it has the
specific meaning of misleading somebody thinking that they've done you... to make
them think you've done them a favor when you really haven't done
them a favor and as a result of which they feel indebted
to you, and they feel, you know, gratitude towards you, which is
undeserved gratitude.
So what's the גניבת דעת gneivat da'at here? Presumably, there's a certain
amount of גניבת דעת gneivat da'at that you're selling... you know, how
do you imagine the non-Jew's feeling? It's like, oh, there's a טריפה,
treifa we can't sell it to the Jews, you guys buy it,
right? So they're always getting like the discards. So if you sell
them, so if you actually take a meat that you could have
sold to Jews, you had removed the גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh. and
instead I'm going to give it to you because you're my friend
the non-Jew and I took this right out of my butcher store
and I'm giving it to you, they feel... feel more sense of
gratitude and being respected. If you're selling, if you're giving it to
me because, "Sure you're giving it to me because you didn't want
to go through the trouble of removing the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh.
and to sell it to your Jews so you give me your
discards." Okay, so then they don't feel the same degree of gratitude.
So the reason that you are allowed to sell it to them
whole but not cut up is if you sell it to them
whole they'll see that you did not remove the... well actually I
didn't exactly describe that correctly because that would still... no no no
that's right. The fact you didn't remove the גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh
they'll... and therefore they won't feel undue gratitude. They'll understand they're getting
the discards like you normally give them the discards. So they're grateful
that you gave them the meat but they're not going to feel
undue gratitude. If however you chopped it up into you know nice
cuts and they can't see the גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh then they
might feel undue gratitude. Then they might actually feel you actually gave
them something you could have sold to your fellow Jews and you're
giving me some nice chop of meat that isn't the discards.
But it's really טריפה, treifa right?
It's really has a גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. No no, it's chopped
up already.
Yeah,
oh it's chopped up but he didn't take out the גיד הנשה.
gid hanasheh You didn't take out the גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. Okay,
so that's the concern. The concern is it's a place where Jews
won't buy from the non-Jew, that's not a concern at all. But
the concern is don't sell the non-Jew a piece of meat that
he thinks you could have sold to Jews. That's גניבת דעת. gneivat
daat. And that's the one you... well oh so you could tell
him but if you didn't tell him then you can't. Okay we
are going to see that you can just tell somebody. Okay so
that's obviously it's not I don't know it's not פשט it doesn't
seem to be that the משנה Mishnah concerned about גניבת דעת gneivat
daat it seems the משנה Mishnah more directly concerned about כשרות kashrut
but the גמרא Gemara is focusing on that issue.
Wait so let me make sure I understand. So we're saying this
is a place that אין מכריזין ein machrizin
and therefore Jews won't buy from him so there's no concern that
if you sell it Jews will buy. The concern is that if
you sell it to him if you sell him a piece that
he knows there's a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh in it or you've
told him but he knows there's a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh then
he'll understand you're giving him the piece that you won't sell to
the Jews. But if you sell him a piece that there is
a גיד but he doesn't realize there's a גיד then he has
undue sense of gratitude.
Which means chopped up one which you just didn't remove the גיד
הנשה. gid hanasheh, Exactly.
Okay. דאמר שמואל de-amar Shmuel because שמואל Shmuel says אסור לגנוב דעת
הבריות assur lignov daat ha-beriyot you cannot steal the knowledge of people,
you cannot mislead people to have this sense of gratitude ואפילו דעתו
של עובד כוכבים va-afilu daato shel oved kochavim even for a non-Jew
it is inappropriate.
והא דשמואל ve-ha d-Shmuel this story of שמואל Shmuel was not said
explicitly this position it was inferred. How do you know this?
דשמואל הוה קא עבר במעברא. de-Shmuel hava ka avar be-mavra. שמואל Shmuel
was passing by on a what's it called a ford?
Bridge. מעברא mavra is a boat. What are those boats called? Ferry.
Ferry that takes you across the river. Okay so anyway he was
passing by on that. אמר
ליה לשמעיה amar lei le-shamayei he said to his assistant פייסיה למעבוריה
payseiah le-mavoriah go and you know work it out with the ferryman
meaning do something nice for him because he's doing us this favor
of bringing us across the bridge. פייסיה payseiah he did it so
he did something for him he gave him something we'll see what
he gave him in a minute. ואיקפיד ve-ikpeid and שמואל Shmuel was
upset. So מאי טעמא איקפיד mai taama ikpeid why did he get
upset? People remember the story that שמואל Shmuel got upset.
Okay so אמר אביי amar Abaye אביי Abaye says תרנגולת טריפה הואי
tarnegolat treifa havai because it was a טריפה treifa chicken that he
gave to the ferryman and it was a non-Jewish ferryman and it
was implicitly or presented as or implicitly understood to be a כשר
kosher chicken. So that's exactly analogous right? Meaning of course the ferryman
doesn't care one way or the other but he feels a different
sense of gratitude if you give him something you could have eaten
as opposed to giving him your discards and something you could not
have eaten. And that's why שמואל Shmuel is upset so you see
the concern of גניבת דעת. gneivat daat. רבא אמר Rava amar that
was what אביי Abaye said. That was אביי Abaye's sort of the
way he remembered the story and how he interpreted שמואל Shmuel's right.
רבא Rava says no no no you got the story wrong. אנפקא
אמר ליה anpaka amar lei he told him to have him drink
some אנפקא anpaka
לאשקויי ואשקויי חמרא מזיגא. le-ashkuyei ve-ashkuyei chamra maziga. He told him to
have him drink some אנפקא anpaka and instead he had him drink
mixed wine. Now what's אנפקא? anpaka? So רש"י Rashi says it means
right obviously something better so רש"י Rashi says it means unmixed undiluted
wine which is very strong and he went and he had him
drink diluted wine. The רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom has one explanation like
that but the other explanation he says is if you look at
the end of yeah so maybe it means stronger I don't know.
You look at the last word the end of the last words
of the first wide line of רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom דאיכא דאמרי
de-ika de-amri אנפקא anpaka and then the first words of the second
line זהו אספרגוס. zehu asparagus. So there's some type of asparagus drink
which was maybe a very healthy drink and instead he gave him
some mixed wine.
Like that celery soda you know.
Okay now of course that is hard to imagine according to רבינו
Rabbeinu either explanation how that's גניבת דעת gneivat daat because you assume
that as soon as he puts the liquid to his lips he'll
understand immediately that it's not asparagus and that it's not you know
strong wine it's diluted wine.
He'll perceive the גניבת דעת gneivat daat I mean
that's what I just said.
No no forget about how it tastes because it's not like unless
he heard שמואל Shmuel say it.
That's what I mean. Meaning that however it's presented as soon as
he tastes it he'll know it's not what it was. Oh, you're
assuming the guy even told him what it was.
No, שמואל Shmuel says it here.
Even if the guy didn't tell him what it was, even if
he had certain assumptions, what's the גניבת דעת geneivat da'at if he
finds out two seconds later when he tries to drink it? Now
we are going to see cases, interestingly, in the גמרא Gemara, later
on, and I'm curious about your thoughts about this, where there is
a case of גניבת דעת geneivat da'at where the person actually does
find out later and it's still considered גניבת דעת geneivat da'at because
for a period of time, the person felt a sense of gratitude.
Now, you might feel, wouldn't the sense afterwards of being tricked
override the initial sense of gratitude? And maybe you could argue it
won't. There was still that sense that doesn't go away even if
afterwards you realize, or maybe it does, but maybe there's a problem
of just even for a time period creating that sense of gratitude,
even if it's not acted upon, even if the person does find
out afterwards, which is quite interesting. We will see that in the
גמרא. Gemara So now, וכי מכלל מאי? Vechi michlal mai? Who cares
that it was inferred? The גמרא Gemara sometimes asks that. Sometimes it
just happens to point out we inferred it, but sometimes the גמרא
Gemara just says, well, why did you bother mentioning that it was
inferred? What do I care? Bottom line, the point is the same.
And then it almost always says, oh, because actually maybe there's a
different interpretation of the story. So actually when it says that it
was inferred, it actually says you can't be a hundred percent certain
this really is the position. Okay. And so now we're going to
hear here how there could be a different interpretation. למאן דאמר טרפה
הוי אמר ליה. Leman de'amar treifa havei amar lei.
So according to the one that says it was a non-kosher chicken,
so maybe אמר ליה אמאי תשרה איסורא? amar lei amai tishra issura?
Maybe שמואל's Shmuel concern was not that he was misleading the non-Jew,
maybe שמואל's Shmuel concern was that he said, how would you leave
a טרפה treifa chicken around for so long? You might come to
eat from it accidentally. So it had nothing to do with what
he gave, that he gave it to the non-Jew, it had to
do with the fact that שמואל Shmuel said, what the heck are
you doing with the non-kosher chicken in your possession? Okay. ולמאן דאמר
אנפקא אמר ליה לאשקויי. U'leman de'amar anfaka amar lei le'ashkuyei. And according
to the one that said he made him drink this אנפקא, anfaka,
which is again, let's say, this undiluted wine, so אנפקא חי משמע.
anfaka chai mashma.
So אנפקא anfaka means means something that is raw. This obviously makes
it fit better
with the explanation that it's undiluted wine as opposed to something totally
different. Now big deal, that's still the point. So the point is
the way רש״י Rashi says this, שמואל Shmuel got upset that he
didn't listen to what שמואל Shmuel said, not that he gave the
non-Jew something that was less quality than the non-Jew might have expected.
Because I told you give him this, what are you doing giving
him something else? So that was his concern. His concern wasn't about
the misrepresentation to the non-Jew; the concern was that. So here the
גמרא Gemara leaves it a little bit unclear, uncertain whether there's a
concern about גניבת דעת geneivat da'at for non-Jews. The רמב״ם Rambam rules
that there is.
And it's interesting, though, I mean, it doesn't seem like there's a
question of is there גניבת דעת, geneivat da'at, as we're going to
switch to in a minute, it seems like does it apply to
non-Jews? And the reason I mentioned this is, on one hand, we
would hope that of all of these sort of interpersonal and ethical
issues, Jews and non-Jews are treated the same, but we do know
in הלכה that is not always the case, which raises important challenges
and questions when we get to those סוגיות sugyot in בבא קמא,
Bava Kamma, so just wait whatever sixty years. Anyway, but I will
say the interesting thing, the point is is that there's a question
whether let's say stealing is אסור assur from non-Jews, but it seems
like the גמרא Gemara is more prepared to say that גניבת דעת
geneivat da'at is forbidden than stealing per se. And there you actually
rule that stealing is also forbidden from non-Jews. So
in the end, it's consistent and you would say it's קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. But there is a position, it's interesting to note that
in the גמרא, Gemara maybe you could say, well, maybe you can't
steal money, maybe גניבת דעת geneivat da'at isn't so bad, but there's
actually a possibility to even split it the other way. And what's
that about? So it is interesting to note, and I should point
this out, that the רמב״ם Rambam puts גניבת דעת geneivat da'at not
in הלכות גניבה וגזילה, Hilchot Gneiva ve'Gzeila, which you wouldn't expect anyway,
but in הלכות דעות, Hilchot De'ot, meaning speaking about the question about
general character traits. Which means that by doing it, to what degree
are you injuring the other person? Because you could have said that.
The fact that you feel gratitude toward me and you might even
act on it, in a way, I am cheating you. I'm getting
something from you that I don't deserve. But the רמב״ם Rambam more
emphasizes that the problem is that my character,
that I mislead people and I have them feel that way towards
me. So that raises an important point here again, which is a
general issue to thinking about various sort of behaviors. Interpersonal or צער
בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim has been a general theme that we've
dealt with and so on, is how much is it about the,
there are two elements always: the other person and what you're doing
to them or the animal and how the animal is suffering, and
what you're doing to yourself and how your own character is influenced
by the way you act towards other people.
So it is interesting to sort of think about that and although
we do know that the גמרא Gemara sometimes does not always have
the best
attitude towards non-Jews or the most sort of egalitarian attitude towards
non-Jews, that maybe that's here דוקא davka it's pointing it out. Now
again, so the question is why is it pointing it out? Is
it pointing it out because this is maybe an expression that more
than other גמרות that we actually have to treat non-Jews equally? totally
to Jews, or is this because of the other issue I'm saying,
which is as I pointed out in the רמב״ם, Rambam, which is
that there's also a question about how these actions influence me and
what they do to my character.
So anyway it's worth thinking about. Yes.
So I'm just trying to understand. According to the גניבת דעת geneivat
da'at issue, it's only a problem to send him a chopped up
whatever it is hunk of meat which had a גיד הנשה gid
hanasheh in it. Let's say another part. Let's say it's the breast
or whatever it is, and you send him a chopped up breast.
That's not a problem from גניבת דעת? geneivat da'at?
No, why is it a problem? If it's something that would be
sold in my store, so then he has the right sense of
gratitude towards me.
No, because it could have been a טרפה. treifa. Right.
So it would have been an equal problem to send him a
טרפה treifa without telling him it's a טרפה.
treifa. Yes, so we are saying that. Yes.
Alright. Okay. So
now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. תניא, Tanya, now we get to
the discussion of גניבת דעת. geneivat da'at. That was about for non-Jew,
now we get to the discussion straight away. היה רבי מאיר אומר,
Haya Rabbi Meir omer, Rabbi Meir said, אל יסרב אדם לחבירו לסעוד
אצלו, al yesarev adam lechavero lis'od etzlo, a person should not pressure
his friend to eat by him, ויודע בו שאינו סועד, veyodeia bo
she-eino so'ed, and he knows that he is not available to eat
by him. So the person says come you'll have a meal by
me etc. I know you have to go right to Cincinnati today
tomorrow. No no no come over I'm having whatever. So you feel
very guilty or grateful etc. and I know that I'm not even
going to have to have you come at my meal. So that's
the גניבת דעת geneivat da'at problem.
So this is someone who you know can't like actually make it
as opposed to the פתח לו חבית patach lo chavit
story, right, where
he knew he doesn't generally go.
Right right.
No no no not if you're really trying to get him to
come and you're really trying to persuade him that's not the problem.
The problem here is that
you are extending an invitation that you know will not be taken
up. Now the question is let's say people know that you do
it out of respect and not because and not that and like
certain people they can't make it to your wedding but you go
ahead and you invite them because they'd be highly offended not to
be invited and you invite them to show because in real you
would love to have them. If they are able to get on
a plane and come a thousand miles you would love to have
them. The fact that they're not going to you still want to
show them that respect. That's not what we're talking about. We're talking
about that a
person that you basically don't want to have the person over and
you're doing it as a way of making them think you do
so that then they will have that false sense of gratitude. Okay.
ולא ירבה לו בתקרובת ויודע שאינו מקבל. Velo yerbeh lo betikrovet veyodeia
she-eino mekabel.
Don't send a lot of gifts knowing that they won't accept, but
at least they'll feel grateful that I'm sending them the gifts.
And he'll send them back. Right. ולא יפתח לו חביות המכורות לחנוני.
Velo yiftach lo chavyot hamuchurot le-chanvani.
Do not open for them barrels of wine that are anyway pre-sold
to the store owner אלא אם כן הודיעו, ela im ken hodio,
and there's informing them. If you inform them it's okay. What does
that mean? It means you come to my house and I open
up a bottle of wine. Now I know we're only going to
have a glass and I'm going to have to leave the rest
of the bottle out and it'll probably go bad or certainly won't
be as good. Okay but you are such a nice guest that
I'm willing to open up the whole bottle of wine just for
you even though we're not going to be able to finish it.
Now that's one thing if it's a bottle. What if it's a
whole barrel? As soon as you open it up it affects the
quality of the wine. If you come to my house and I
open up a fresh barrel for you that's a real sign that
I respect you as a guest. Now so but don't do that
if the reason I'm able to do it is because as soon
as you leave I have this wine pre-sold to the store owner,
you know not for the whole barrel whatever, if I sell him
a half barrel so I buy a half barrel and therefore I'm
really not going to lose anything out of the deal because I'm
just going to sell it maybe a little bit because it was
opened but the store owner will sell it all in a day
so I'm not really losing anything out of the deal. So you
think I did this big deal and actually I'm protected because I'm
just going to sell to the store owner. Okay but if I
tell you about that that's fine. ולא יאמר לו סוך שמן מפך
ריקן. Velo yomar lo soch shemen mipach reikan. Now here's the case
where even if it turns out to be to be able to
be discovered right these other cases couldn't be discovered but don't tell
him here why don't you put some oil put some oil on
your hands or whatever here take some oil like אברהם Avraham with
the מלאכים malachim and the pitcher is empty. Now again I'm not
it's not clear to me does that mean because you know he'll
turn you down and you really it's like this other case where
you really didn't weren't intending or does it even mean don't give
him the pitcher and walk away and for a few minutes he
feels good and even though at two seconds later he feels this
guy tricked me. Or maybe he doesn't really trick me maybe he
feels נבך nebach he didn't realize that the pitcher was empty. So
he gives you the benefit of a doubt and in the end
right but this is going to be interesting cases where you might
get found out and it's still a problem. ואם בשביל כבודו מותר.
Ve-im bishvil kevodo mutar.
If it's a way of showing honor it's permissible. So I gave
you an example of like inviting somebody to your wedding where they
feel honored but there's also the sense of being honored in front
of other guests. So therefore if you're doing it as a way
that other people will see how you honor this person you're not
you know so it could it's a little funny like on the
one hand you're going through the motions it's not real but it's
going through the motions in a sense you're not giving them something
an empty thing because what you're actually giving him is the honor
that he's getting from everybody else. So you here I have pre-sold
this barrel I'm not going to tell you about it but if
everybody sees I'm opening the barrel because you walked in the door
when they were here I didn't open the new barrel. You are
oh Micah let me open up a new barrel of wine everybody
thinks you're a חשוב chashuv person so there it's you know that's
there even though even though you might Micah might also feel a
certain gratitude. is misplaced, there's a benefit that comes to it that
I'm doing it in front of everybody else and everybody else sort
of now sees the respect that I am giving you. But so
it's not clear that the אם ידעת ליה im yidatleh a little
bit... Well that's the question. Is אם בשביל כבודו im bishvil kvodo
means that you, the recipient, are aware that it's משום כבודו, mishum
kvodo, then it's more like just a variation of הודעו hodio and
so on. Or it might just be that it's counterbalanced by the
honor that accrues to you as a result of that, that in
the end, what you even feel more grateful to me about is
not that I took the loss of opening the barrel, but that
you received such honor in front of everybody around the table. And
that's genuine. You did receive that honor. Okay, fine. איני? eini? Is
this really true? והא עולא איקלע לבי רב יהודה. veha Ulla ikla
levei Rav Yehuda. עולא Ulla came to the house of רב יהודה.
Rav Yehuda. פתח לו חביתא המכורה לחנווני. patach lo chavita hamchura lechanvani.
So he opened up for him barrels that had already been pre-sold.
So you see he did it. So the גמרא's Gemara like, how
did the גמרא Gemara know? Maybe a day later they saw him
sell it to the חנווני. chanvani. So the גמרא Gemara says, אודועי
אודעיה. oduei odaiei. He told him about it. Then that solves all
the problems. ואיבעית אימא, veiva'it eima, if you want you could say,
שאני עולא דחביב ליה לרב יהודה. shani Ulla dechaviv leh leRav Yehuda.
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda really loved רב יהודה... Rav Yehuda... I'm sorry,
he was loved by רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דבלאו הכי נמי פתח
ליה ומסתכלי. debilav hachi nami patach leh umistaklei.
He would have opened it up for him even if, you know,
even if it had not been pre-sold.
So as I said,
if I would have done it anyway, I don't need to tell
you, because then, you know, you feel very grateful to me, but
I'm not like tricking you or fooling you. In this particular case,
I didn't suffer loss, but I would have done it regardless. Okay,
I know some people that'll like really מחמיר machmir on this, you
know, that somebody will, I mean, you know, come out with whatever,
open up a bottle of wine to say, I just want you
to know, I was planning on opening up this wine anyway.
Now you make me feel bad. Right.
Well,
I understand that they're doing it because they're מחמיר machmir about גניבת
דעת, gneivat da'at, so I don't feel bad about it. Yeah, I
know, I understand. So that raises interesting questions which we'll take, get
to on the עמוד ב amud beis about the גמרא Gemara about...
so let's hold off on this.
Whether they're showing their honesty?
Exactly. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. He says, לא ילך אדם לבית האבל
ובידו לגין המקשקש. lo yelech adam leveit ha'avel uvyado laging hamkashkesh.
A person should not go to a mourner's house having like a,
you know, a sort of a barrel, or like a לגין, lagin,
which is like, you know, a container of wine that is rattling,
which means not really rattling, but whatever, you know, slosh, which means
it's non-full. You say, oh here, have some, you know, I brought
you some wine, and then they open it up and they realize
it's not full. Now again, you say, so where's the gratitude as
soon as they open it up? So again, either there's a problem
of גניבת דעת gneivat da'at even for a few minutes, which is
interesting because you would think it would automatically be corrected, and you'd
be, anyway, but if somebody is doing it, they must think they're
going to get some, you know, they must have a reason why
it's in their interest to do it. So it must be that
they think that maybe the אבל, avel, you know, אבל avel will
give me the benefit of the doubt. They'll think that I was,
I thought it was full and in the end it wound up
not being full. But again, you can't explain all the cases like
this. Let's keep on reading. ולא ימלאנו מים מפני שמתעהו. velo yemala'enu
mayim mipnei shemat'ehu. Do not fill it with water, bring him something
that looks like a bottle of wine but it's actually filled with
water. So there, you know, what type of, what type of gratitude
are they going to feel with with me? I mean, they can't
even think I made an honest, an honest mistake. I gave them
a bottle filled with water, you know? So it's hard, I really
don't have a full handle on this. Like for a moment he
thinks oh very nice, he brought me a bottle of wine. Then
he opens up and says oh it was just water. Maybe he
doesn't think I'm intentionally deceiving him, but is he really going to
still feel gratitude? Maybe the גמרא's concerned it'll still be some remnants
of the original feeling even though now I know better, you know?
But if, if I knew I was actually deceived, I can't believe
how there should be a problem, how that wouldn't completely overweigh. Okay.
ואם יש שם חבר עיר מותר. veim yesh sham chaver ir mutar.
If however there is a... רש״י Rashi says this means if there's
a gathering of people in the אבל avel house, and by me
giving it to him, it gives him honor that people say, oh
look, רבי Winzer came and he gave this person a bottle of
wine. So then even if he opens it up and sees that
it was just water, he's still going to feel very grateful that
I did it, I gave him something that would make other people
sort of, you know, give him respect. So that obviously is something
very real, the respect that he gets. Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan.
We taught. לא ימכור אדם לחבירו סנדל של מתה בכלל של חיה.
lo yimkor adam lachaveiro sandal shel metah bichlal shel chayah. Now this
is not just גניבת דעת, gneivat da'at, this might actually be misrepresentation
in terms of just
מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, like fraud. Don't sell somebody a sandal made
out of the leather of an animal that naturally died בכלל של
חיה, bichlal shel chayah, so that the person is going to assume
that it's leather that came from שחיטה shechting a healthy animal, because
leather that came from an old dead animal that died a natural
death is obviously lower quality. So don't sell them leather let them,
having them think it's higher quality, that's the presumption, when it's really
lower quality. מפני שני דברים. mipnei shnei devarim. Two reasons. אחד מפני
שמתעהו. echad mipnei shemat'ehu. You, you are,
you know, you're misleading him. But also there's sense like fraud is
really going on here more than just גניבת דעת. gneivat da'at. ואחד
מפני הסכנה. ve'echad mipnei hasakana. And also because of a question about...
about physical danger because the animal died, maybe it's got some bad
stuff going on in its body and its leather that's now going
to get onto your foot if you're wearing it. Okay.
ולא ישגר אדם לחברו, Velo yeshager adam le-chavero, a person should not
send his friend חבית של יין ושמן צף על פיה, chavis shel
yayin ve-shemen tzaf al piha, so that was as a sale, sale
obviously there's a much bigger problem about fraud. Now we're dealing with
issues about גניבת דעת. geneivas da'as. Don't send as a gift to
your friend a barrel of wine ושמן צף על פיה ve-shemen tzaf
al piha with some with some honey on the on the top
of it, because honey is, honey is, honey is more expensive, I'm
sorry, oil, excuse me, oil. Oil is more expensive, maybe I'm thinking
Rosh Hashanah. Oil is more expensive than wine. So a person opens
up a barrel and they see the top layer is oil. Oh
my God, this guy sent me a whole barrel of oil! And
then when they get to, they don't realize that it's eighty percent
underneath wine. And I guess oil floats on wine, same as oil
floats on wine, same as oil floats on water. So, or does
water flo- how does oil float on water? Oil floats on water.
Okay, oil floats on water. Anyway, so, again the funny thing here
is that where's the גניבת דעת? geneivas da'as? As soon as the
person gets later into the barrel, he realizes what's going on. Again,
so I really don't have a full answer unless again (a) he
can't know that you intentionally deceived him, then you would imagine that
that would totally counteract any sense of gratitude. Or (b), it was,
you know, and not, a, I'd say
a and b is that, you know, maybe he,
there's some remnant of the sense of gratitude that remains even after
he realizes that you didn't do for him as big of a
deal that you thought he would. I suppose the other possibility is,
and this I guess goes back to my question about is the
problem about the person you're affecting or about your own character traits,
that even if, even if the person does realize afterwards and is
angry at you, the fact that you were engaged in an act
of deception even for a brief period of time, meaning, let's imagine
a scenario, right? First of all you could imagine a scenario where
I want you to feel grateful for me just for a few
minutes. We're signing a business deal, whatever, I want to butter you
up something for a few minutes, so I've achieved my results that
you felt grateful for those few minutes. Or maybe even if there
was no actual benefit and afterwards you get really angry at me,
maybe I just shouldn't be involved in acts of deception regardless. But
still you wonder, like, what type of שכל sechel would I do
to do to bother doing this if the end result was going
to be bad? You know, so there's got to be some scenario
where you still, the guy will still have some sense of gratitude
or you exploited that feeling for a period of time.
Yes. Today wine costs much more than oil. Right. So, but so
this would still apply?
Well no, whatever appropriate application it would be. I mean but the,
you know, the theory applies. Okay.
Okay, so where are we? ומעשה באחד ששיגר לחברו חבית של יין
ושמן צף על פיה, U-ma'aseh be-echad she-shigar le-chavero chavis shel yayin ve-shemen
tzaf al piha, somebody sent a person a barrel of wine with
oil on the top, והלך וזימן עליה אורחין, ve-halach ve-zimen aleha orchin,
and the guy decided he's going to have, whoa, he had a
barrel of oil! I'm going to have a feast! And he invited
over a dozen people, and, you know, all I have to do
is provide the bread. Bread and oil, what can you do better
for a meal? ונכנסו, Ve-nikhnasu, and they all came in, מצא שהיא
של יין, matza she-hi shel yayin,
and he found
that it was wine underneath, and oh my God, and he was
so terribly embarrassed, וחנק את עצמו, ve-chanak et atzmo, and he strangled
himself. Now you could have sort of said that that happened like
by accident, like he choked on the wine thinking it was oil,
but Rashi actually says, no, it actually means he like committed suicide
out of his anguish that he was so embarrassed. And now we're
going to have a couple of other suicide stories. So, where were
we? ואין האורחין רשאין ליתן ממה שלפניהם לבנו ולבתו של בעל הבית
אלא אם כן נטלו רשות מבעל הבית. Ve-ein ha-orchin rasha'in litten mimmash
shelifneichem livno u-levitto shel ba'al ha-bayis ella im ken natlu reshut miba'al
ha-bayis. So we're not going anymore about גניבת דעת, geneivas da'as, but
about food related stuff and proper behavior. Guests cannot give from the
food that's put in front of them to the kids because obviously
the guests are getting the better food than the kids in the
household. You're a guest in the household, they put a nice steak
in front of you, the kids are getting I don't know applesauce,
and they're looking very jealously at the steak. You don't cut a
piece of your steak and give it to the kid, אלא אם
כן נטלו רשות מבעל הבית, ella im ken natlu reshut miba'al ha-bayis,
unless the owner has given you permission. Because maybe he spent special
money, it's still about a sense of like honoring people with gifts,
you know, with food. Maybe he spent extra money to do something
very nice for you and he's got this beautiful dish prepared, and
no, the kids will have something else. He's spending money on you,
so don't give it to his kids.
Unless the, unless the, unless the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis has given
permission. ומעשה באחד שזימן ג' אורחין בשני בצורת, U-ma'aseh be-echad she-zimen gimel
orchin bi-shenei batzores, somebody invited over three guests at a time of
famine, ולא היה לו להניח לפניהם אלא כשלש ביצים. velo hayah lo
lehaniach lifneichem ella ke-shalosh beitzim. All he had to put in front
of them were three eggs, meaning that's okay, you know, that he
had three eggs, at a time of famine, that's pretty חשוב, chashuv,
so each one of them got an egg. בא בנו של בעל
הבית, Ba beno shel ba'al ha-bayis, so the son came around, he
was obviously pretty hungry, it was a time of famine, נטל אחד
מהן, natal echad me-hen, אחד מהם, echad me-hem, חלקו ונתנו לו. chelko
u-netano lo.
So one of the guests took his portion, his egg, and gave
it to the kid. Oh, poor kid, I'll, I'll forgo my meal.
Give, and he gave the egg to the kid. וכן שני וכן
שלישי, Ve-chen sheni ve-chen shelishi, and then the kid went with his
puppy eyes to the other two guests and got their eggs also.
Okay. בא אביו של תינוק, Ba aviv shel tinok,
the father of the kid came, מצאו שאוחז. matzo she-ochez. he says
that he was sort of swallowing one in his mouth, ושתים בידיו,
ushtayim beyadav,
and he had the other two in his two hands, וחבטו בקרקע,
v'chivto bakarka,
he smacked him on the ground or, you know, he threw him
on the ground, ומת, umate, and the kid died. So he got
father a little, you know, overreacted and and that
and it was a terrible outcome. כיון שראתה אמו, keivan sherata imo,
and when his mother saw what happened, עלתה לגג ונפלה ומתה, alta
legag v'nafla u'meisa,
she went up to the roof and fell and died, presumably since
she killed herself, ואף הוא עלה לגג ונפל ומת, v'af hu ala
legag v'nafal u'mais, and then he saw that the whole family has
now been wiped out, he did the same thing. So look at
this, three lives were lost because the guest did, you know, didn't
do what they were supposed, also the father overreacted, but okay. So
anyway, certainly impressive how tragic the outcomes can be. So the same
way we had the tragic outcome in one case of misrepresenting the
food that you're sending, here's another one. So, you know, the heavy
responsibility about being keeping these types of guidelines when it comes to
specifically I mean this seems very specifically around issues of these sort
of food issues, but just in general.
Okay. So the גמרא says,
אמר רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, amar Rabi Elazar ben Yaakov, על דבר
זה נהרגו ג' נפשות מישראל, al davar zeh nehergu gimel nefashot m'Yisrael,
because of this thing that somebody gave to the kids without permission,
three Jewish lives were lost. מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what
of course, what are you telling us? We can figure that out
too. פשיטא? No. דכולה רבי אלעזר בן יעקב היא, d'kula Rabi Elazar
ben Yaakov hi, this just ends with Rabi Elazar ben Yaakov saying
it to tell us that this whole משנה, Mishnah. or this whole
ברייתא braita rather, is all the teaching of Rabi Elazar ben Yaakov,
because and therefore we gave him his voice at the end. Okay.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. And we're still with גניבת דעת. gneivat da'at.
No, because we have ten minutes left and we're behind. השולח ירך
לחבירו ושלמה אינו צריך ליטול הימנה גיד הנשה. hasholeach yarech lachaveiro ushleima
eino tzarich litol heimena gid hanasheh.
So now we're going to go back to the question about removing
the גיד and then we'll get back to גניבת דעת gneivat da'at
a little bit later. If you sent a side to your friend,
if it's whole, you do not have to remove the גיד הנשה.
gid hanasheh Now it's not to the non-Jew, but the guy also
has to know whether he has a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh he
needs to remove. So if it's whole, he doesn't have to, you
don't have to remove it, it's obvious and he'll remove it. חתוכה
צריך ליטול הימנה גיד הנשה. chatucha tzarich litol heimena gid hanasheh. If
you're going to chop chop it up, you have to because he'll
assume that, you know, because then, you know, you have to A,
I don't even know if it's possible to remove the גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh. once it's chopped up, but even if it is, he'll
assume it's been removed. So therefore you have to remove it before
you send it to him. ובעובדי כוכבים, uv'ovdei kochavim, when it comes
to a non-Jew, בין חתוכה בין שלמה אינו צריך ליטול הימנה גיד
הנשה, bein chatucha bein shleima eino tzarich litol heimena gid hanasheh,
whether whole or chopped you don't have to. Presumably because, presumably because
it's a place where people don't buy from non-Jews. Okay.
wait, so we said
we said that in the משנה Mishnah.
that you can't...
Yes, because the משנה Mishnah, we had ways of explaining that it
was place where people could buy from non-Jews, etc. So just hold
it, I'll explain it after. Okay, and the גמרא will explain. Non-Jews,
you can sell it to them, presumably because it's a place where
people won't buy from non-Jews. ומפני ב' דברים אמרו אין מוכרין נבלות
וטרפות לעובדי כוכבים. mipnei bet devarim amru ein mochrin nevelot utreifot l'ovdei
kochavim. There are two reasons you cannot sell non-kosher meat to non-Jews.
אחד מפני שמטעהו, echad mipnei shemat'ehu, one is because you mislead him.
So there you see exactly the reason that, you know, felt a
little bit like it was forced into the משנה, here in this
ברייתא braita it's explicit that that you make them feel grateful that
they're, you know, this גניבת דעת, gneivat da'at, that they're now going
to feel grateful, because they're going to think that you're selling them
kosher meat when you're really selling them the discard. So don't sell
them the discard unless you tell them it's the discard. Otherwise they'll
feel grateful inappropriately. ואחד שמא יחזור וימכרנה לישראל אחר. v'echad shema yachzor
v'yimkerena l'Yisrael acher.
Another concern is even if you do tell them, you can't sell
them טריפה treifa. because they'll go back and sell it to Jews.
Now we've got a problem because first you told me I can
sell to the non-Jew that I can sell, send a non-Jew the
גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, so presumably I'm not afraid that they're going
to go back and sell it to Jews. I can specifically send
a non-Jew the גיד הנשה gid hanasheh and I'm not afraid that
they're going to go back and sell it to Jews. So presumably
it's a place where Jews don't buy. Now it's telling me don't
sell them טריפה treifa meat because they'll sell it to Jews. So
what's the scenario? Is it a scenario where Jews do buy from
non-Jews or don't buy from non-Jews? So we will see the גמרא
will work this out. ולא יאמר אדם לעובד כוכבים קח לי בדינר
זה בשר. v'lo yomar adam l'oved kochavim kach li b'dinar zeh basar.
Don't have a non-Jew, send him to the butcher with a, you
know, ten bucks to buy you a piece of meat. מפני ב'
דברים, mipnei bet devarim, for two reasons. אחד מפני האנסים, echad mipnei
ha'anasim, the people the strong-armed people. What does that mean? It means
that the non-Jew will go, I mean again, we're talking about a
very particular context, not general statement about non-Jews, but in the particular
context in which this ברייתא braita was being written, you know, under
Roman domination in the land of Israel, so the non-Jew might go
to the Jewish land store owner and force him to give him
the meat without having to pay for it. And he'll pocket the
money. Don't go send him to the Jewish whatever, you know, because
then as a result of you he's going to pocket the money
and force the guy to give him the meat for nothing.
ואחד שמא ימכרו לו נבלות וטרפות. v'echad shema yimkru lo nevelot utreifot.
They'll say oh, he's a non-Jew, I'll sell him the נבלות וטרפות,
nevelot utreifot, no problem. And then he'll come back and he'll bring
it back to you. So now we've got a very confusing thing.
First you say don't sell to the non-Jews because he's going to
sell it back to the Jew. Then we talk about a case
where don't send the non-Jew to the store because they'll sell him
meat. I thought you're not allowed to sell the non-Jew meat, right?
Then you and you also say at the beginning go ahead and
send him the meat with the... with without the גיד הנשה gid
hanasheh removed, nothing to be afraid of. Why is there nothing to
be afraid of? He's going to go back and sell it to
the Jew. So it keeps on going back and forth between the
assumption of are we concerned that people are selling meat to non-Jews?
Are we concerned that Jews are buying meat from non-Jews? The assumptions
are shifting. And the גמרא recognizes this, so let's take a look.
So אמר מר, amar mar, let's try to get a handle on
this. עובד כוכבים בין שלמה בין חתוכה אינו צריך ליטול הימנו גיד
הנשה. oved kochavim bein sheleimah bein chatuchah einu tzarich litol heimenu gid
hanasheh. When you sell it to a non-Jew you don't have to
remove the גיד. במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what's the case? אילימא במקום
שמכריזין, eilima b'makom shemachrizin, and they announce. To announce means you're allowed
to buy from a non-Jew because you'll otherwise because otherwise you'll have
heard an announcement. So חתוכה אמאי אינו צריך ליטול הימנו גיד הנשה?
chatuchah amai einu tzarich litol heimenu gid hanasheh? Why do you why
are you allowed to sell him chopped up pieces of meat? כיון
דלא אכריז, keivan d'lo achriz, if there's no announcement אתי למיזבן מיניה,
ati lemizban minei,
meaning presumably we're talking if it's a context where people will buy
from a non-Jew, why can you sell him the גיד הנשה when
it's chopped up? People are going to come to buy it from
him. אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, so the first case of the משנה
that says you can sell the non-Jew
the cut up pieces with the גיד is במקום שאין מכריזין, b'makom
she'ein machrizin, is a place where they don't announce. It's a place
where nobody buys from non-Jews. So the only way the first line
of the משנה that says you can sell it with the גיד
cut up works is if it's a place where nobody buys from
non-Jews. Okay? But that doesn't work with the next line of the
משנה. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the next line of
the משנה. בשני דברים אמרו אין מוכרין נבלות וטרפות לעובד כוכבים. bishnei
devarim amru ein mochrin neveilot u'treifot l'oved kochavim. Don't sell טריפה treifa
meat to non-Jews. אחד מפני שמטעהו, echad mipnei shemat'eihu, one you're misleading
him, ואחד שמא יחזור וימכרנה לישראל אחר, v'echad shema yachzor v'yimkarenah l'Yisrael
acher, because you're afraid he'll turn around and sell it to a
Jew. So that means it's a context where Jews do buy from
non-Jews. ואי במקום שאין מכריזין, v'ei b'makom she'ein machrizin,
if it's a place where there's no announcement and nobody buys from
non-Jews, הא לא אתי למיזבן מיניה, ha lo ati lemizban minei, nobody's
going to buy from him. אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, the middle case
where you're where you don't sell them non-kosher food only makes sense
במקום שמכריזין b'makom shemachrizin where they make announcements and people buy from
Jews. Right? So you get it. The first case says no problem
sell them a גיד הנשה. That only makes sense if nobody's buying
from Jews. I mean nobody's buying from non-Jews. Okay. Next case is
don't sell טרפות, treifos, people will buy from him. So that only
makes sense if people are buying from him. So make up your
mind, what's the scenario? אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the
last case. לא יאמר אדם לעובד כוכבים קח לי בדינר זה בשר.
lo yomar adam l'oved kochavim kach li b'dinar zeh basar. Don't send
him to the store to buy meat. מפני שני דברים, mipnei shnei
devarim, for two reasons. אחד מפני האונסא, echad mipnei ha'onasa, one because
of what do you call it, one because he'll he'll force the
guy to sell without paying, ואחד שמא מוכרין לו נבלות וטרפות, v'echad
shema mochrin lo neveilot u'treifot, he'll sell him non-kosher meat. But I
thought you just said you're not allowed to sell non-kosher meat to
non-Jews? ואי במקום שמכריזין, v'ei b'makom shemachrizin,
if it's a place where you make the announcement, so אי איכא
דהוי טריפה אכרוזי הוו מכרזי. ei ika d'havi treifa achruzei havu machrizei.
First of all, if there was טריפה treifa? out there, they would
have announced it. So you anyway know that they'll be selling it
to the non-Jew and not as the person who sent this guy
to buy it not to take it from him. אלא פשיטא במקום,
ela peshita b'makom, I'm sorry, right, אלא פשיטא במקום שאין מכריזין, ela
peshita b'makom she'ein machrizin, it must be a place where they don't
make announcements and therefore nobody buys from non-Jews.
Right.
If people are selling to non-Jews, you're afraid the store owner's going
to sell to the non-Jew you sent, only it only makes
sense that the store owner could be selling to the non-Jew if
it's a place where nobody buys from non-Jews. It's a place that
אין מכריזין, ein machrizin, they don't make announcements. So again, the גמרא
is pointing it out very clearly that the ברייתא Braita here each
line assumes something else. Let's just review it. The first line says
you could sell them a גיד הנשה, which means you're not afraid
anybody's going to buy from a non-Jew. Okay. Then it says don't
sell them נבלות neveilot and טרפות. treifot. Why? Because you're afraid people
will buy from a non-Jew. Then it says, but if you
can announce it though, you can say I don't sell
them the so why can't you sell? Well let's see the answer.
But first let's understand the problem. Then it says, then it says
don't send the non-Jew to the store because you're afraid people will
sell to the non-Jew, even though a minute ago you said don't
sell to the non-Jew. So make up your mind. Are we afraid
people will buy and therefore nobody is selling? Are we not afraid
and therefore people are selling and they are giving? So the משנה,
it is constantly mixed, it is constantly going back and forth. So
רישא וסיפא במקום שאין מכריזין מציעתא במקום שמכריזין. reisha v'seifa b'makom she'ein
machrizin metziata b'makom shemachrizin.
Do you mean to tell me the beginning and the end is
a place where they don't announce? Again, don't announce means nobody buys
from non-Jews. If nobody buys from non-Jews you can sell them the
גיד הנשה and you can, on the other hand, you
can't send the non-Jew to the store because they'll sell him טרפות.
treifot. And מציעתא, metziata, the middle case, is במקום שמכריזין, b'makom shemachrizin,
has to be a case where people do buy from non-Jews and
therefore don't sell them the טריפה. treifa, So make up your mind,
is it a place where they do announce or they don't announce?
So אמר אביי אין. amar Abaye ein. Yes, that's the case. This
ברייתא Braita is a little inconsistent. רישא וסיפא במקום שאין מכריזין, reisha
v'seifa b'makom she'ein machrizin, the beginning and end is a place where
they do not announce, מציעתא במקום metziata b'makom
and therefore you people can sell to non-Jews and can buy from
non-Jews. can sell to non-Jews and not buy from non-Jews, and מציעתא
במקום שמכריזין, Metziasa b'makom she-machrizin, the middle of the case where they
do announce. And since they announce and people can buy from non-Jews,
therefore you're also not allowed to sell to non-Jews. Okay, so that's
yes, they're talking about different scenarios. רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says
probably what Michael wanted to say, it's basically the same answer except
still different scenarios. כולו במקום שמכריזין, Kulo b'makom she-machrizin, it's all in
places where they make announcements and you're allowed to buy from non-Jews.
רישא וסיפא דהכריזו, Reisha v'Seifa d'achrizu, so the first and last case
they made, they made, if
there was a טריפה treifa out there and they made an announcement.
So because they made an announcement, it is right now, right, if
it's a place where they make announcements, it doesn't mean you always
buy from non-Jews. It means you buy from non-Jews unless there's an
announcement. So Rava says we don't have to talk about different places,
we do have to talk about different scenarios but not different places.
So it's a place where they make announcements. Even in a place
where they make announcements, there are times when you don't buy from
non-Jews when the announcement is in effect. So therefore the first case
and last case that assume that you are not buying from non-Jews
and therefore allow people to sell to non-Jews is when the announcement
was made. When the announcement is made, people won't buy and therefore
you're allowed to sell. That was the beginning and the last case.
מציעתא, Metziasa, the middle case, שלא הכריזו shelo hichrizu was a time
when there was no announcement out there. If there was no announcement
and you happen to have a טריפה on your hand but for
some reason the announcement didn't go out, then you don't sell. Okay,
so again, the first and last cases are assuming that people are
not buying from non-Jews and therefore allow you to sell.
But they are if it's a place they make announcements, right? No,
no.
The beginning and the end are assuming that people are not buying
from non-Jews and therefore you're allowed to sell. The middle case is
assuming people are buying from non-Jews and you're not allowed to sell.
So how do you explain it? Either the first and last case
is a place where there's no announcements are ever made and therefore
don't people buy, or the first and last case are places where
announcements are made but it's at a time when the announcement is
in effect. And since the announcement is in effect, it's a time
when people are not buying from non-Jews and therefore you are not
buying and therefore you're allowed to sell to non-Jews. Okay, whereas in
the middle case when the announcement isn't in effect and people are
buying from non-Jews, that's when you're not allowed to sell. Let's just
give one more answer. I know we're a little over, but let's
just finish it
because רב אשי Rav Ashi finally says that we're talking about not
different scenarios. רב אשי אמר כולו במקום שאין מכריזין. Rav Ashi amar
kulo b'makom she-ein machrizin. It's a place they don't announce normally, therefore
people are not allowed to buy from non-Jews. That's the beginning and
the end, that people are not allowed to buy and therefore they're
allowed to sell because they're not allowed to buy from them. That's
the beginning and the end where you're allowed to sell to a
non-Jew because people aren't buying. Now how about the middle case about
the טריפה? ומציעתא, u-Metziasa,
the middle case about the טריפה, why are you not allowed to
sell them, send them a טריפה if people won't buy from it?
גזרה שמא ימכרנו בפני ישראל, Gezeira shema yimkerenu bifnei Yisrael, we're afraid
that they'll do it, that you'll do it in the presence of
another Jew. So the same way before we had that concern, here
as well we have the concern. Don't, basically the basic rule is
like this. People don't buy from non-Jews and therefore you are allowed
to, what do you call it, people don't buy from non-Jews and
therefore you are allowed to sell to non-Jews, but there's one exception
which is: oh, by the way, don't sell because people are going
to see you and therefore think it's okay. But I don't understand.
If you know, you just told me in general I'm allowed to
sell, so what exactly the difference? So רש״י Rashi points out that
the middle case where it says, excuse me, is a case where
it says
אין מוכרין נבלות וטרפות ein mocherin neveilos u'treifos as opposed to giving
them, as opposed to giving. You can give them the גיד הנשה
because when you give, normally the way you give is you send
it and way to respect, you send it through another party. So
nobody sees you directly giving and you're not doing it at the
person's, you're doing it at the person's private home, there're not people
around. But to sell in the store where there's a lot of
people around, there we're afraid that other people will see and will
assume that oh, he just sold it to the non-Jew, I can
buy it from the non-Jew. Okay, so it's a little complicated, but
basically the upshot is is that in a place where people are
going to buy from the non-Jew, which is never our scenario, you
can't sell, okay? And that would be either in a place where
what's a place people will buy, where they make announcements and no
announcement is in effect. Since since people will buy, you can't sell.
But in a place where people won't buy, which is either a
place where where they never make announcements or they do make announcements
and the announcement is in effect. So in a place where people
won't buy, then you're allowed to sell because what's to be lost
by selling, nobody's going to buy from them. The only thing then
to have to be concerned about is is there a גזרה gezeira
that even in those cases somebody will see me and assume that
it's כשר. kosher. Of course you say why will they assume it's
כשר? kosher? They know you're not allowed to buy from non-Jews. So
that's a real question of these גזרות gezeiros apply. Okay, but we'll
end with, I know we're over actually, but you'll give me, I'm
sorry, we are late, but give me just why one more line
because it just says what the announcement is.
You can sell to a non-Jew, you can sell to a non-Jew
but not in the store. What?
You can sell.
You can sell the meat to a non-Jew but not in the
store.
You can sell the meat to a non-Jew, yes, the way, according
to one of the explanations, the גזירה gezeira would not apply. You
know, yes, that's true. Actually, we will end here because.